<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-16T16:11:19-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Three important presentations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three important presentations" /><published>2019-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-2.html">&lt;p&gt;Dynamica held 3 (!) end of winter semester Colloquia on April 12th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vincent Thibeault presented his plan for his master thesis, in a talk entitled
“Prédiction des régimes de synchronisation sur graphes aléatoires” (Predicting synchronization regimes on random graphs); Xavier Roy-Pomerleau did the same.
His presentation was titled “Inférence d’interactions d’ordre supérieur dans les systèmes complexes” (Inference of higher order interactions in complex systems).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this occasion, Guillaume St-Onge also passed his doctoral entry exam. An important part of the evaluation was a presentation, titled “Theoretical and computational modeling of spreading processes on complex networks”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of them passed their respective tests with excellent grades, and are now free to undertake the next step; for VT and XRP, this will mean writing their M.Sc thesis, while GST can officially begin the active research portion of his PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best of luck to them!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dynamica held 3 (!) end of winter semester Colloquia on April 12th.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NetSci 2019 (bis)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-13.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NetSci 2019 (bis)" /><published>2019-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-13</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-13.html">&lt;p&gt;The three talks for the main conference were well received : Deep learning for dynamical processes on networks (C. Murphy), prediction of synchronization regimes using dimension reduction on graphs (V. Thibeault) and prediction of localization regimes for spreading processes on networks (G. St-Onge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference was a big success, thanks to the Lead Conference Organizer Juniper Lovato and to two Dynamica alumni : Laurent Hébert-Dufresne (Co-Chair for the main conference) and Antoine Allard (Schools Co-Chair).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstracts for the presentations are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/publications.html&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The three talks for the main conference were well received : Deep learning for dynamical processes on networks (C. Murphy), prediction of synchronization regimes using dimension reduction on graphs (V. Thibeault) and prediction of localization regimes for spreading processes on networks (G. St-Onge).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paper published in Computer Physics Communication</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-16.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper published in Computer Physics Communication" /><published>2019-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-16</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/old-16.html">&lt;p&gt;The latest contribution of the network section is available in the July issue of Computer Physics Communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpc.2019.02.008&quot;&gt;Efficient sampling of spreading processes on complex networks using a composition and rejection algorithm&lt;/a&gt; propose an efficient simulation scheme for simple contagion models on networks, represented by a discrete-state and continuous time Markov process. The method hinges on a clever composition and rejection step that allows the efficient sampling of heterogeneous (and time-varying) probability distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to the full text and preprints are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/publications.html&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The latest contribution of the network section is available in the July issue of Computer Physics Communication.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paper published in Physical Review X</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/11/old-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper published in Physical Review X" /><published>2019-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/03/11/old-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/11/old-1.html">&lt;p&gt;The latest contribution of the network section is available in the March issue of Physical Review X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevX.9.011042&quot;&gt;Spectral Dimension Reduction of Complex Dynamical Networks&lt;/a&gt; presents a mathematically sound formalism to coarse grain the high dimensional set of equations governing the evolution of a general deterministic dynamics on a network. The approach leverage the spectral properties of a network, more specifically the dominant eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the adjacency matrix, to perform the reduction. The lower dimensional system can be used to better understand the critical behavior of certain systems and lead the way towards a better comprehension of the robustness and the resilience of complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to the full text and preprints are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/publications.html&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The latest contribution of the network section is available in the March issue of Physical Review X.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NetSci 2019 in Burlington : 3 talks and a strong alumni representation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/28/old-6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NetSci 2019 in Burlington : 3 talks and a strong alumni representation" /><published>2019-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/28/old-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/28/old-6.html">&lt;p&gt;Dynamica performs a hat trick : three members of the network division will attend and give talks during the main conference at NetSci 2019. This 14th edition will be held in Burlington, Vermont, at the end of May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentations will cover diverse topics : the (deep) learning of dynamical processes on complex networks (C. Murphy), the characterization of localization on networks for spreading processes (G. St-Onge) and the prediction of synchronization regimes using dimension reduction on graphs (V.
Thibeault). Details are available on the conference page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond this formidable representation of the current members of the group,
alumni from Dynamica will be particularly active during this annual meeting on network science. Laurent Hébert-Dufresne, now assistant professor in the department of computer science at the University of Vermont, will be Co-Chair for the main conference. Jean-Gabriel Young, James S. McDonnell Fellow at the University of Michigan, will be Co-Chair at the Open NetSci Hackathon, the weekend before the main event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstracts for the presentations are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/publications.html&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dynamica performs a hat trick : three members of the network division will attend and give talks during the main conference at NetSci 2019. This 14th edition will be held in Burlington, Vermont, at the end of May.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prof. Reinhold Blümel (Wesleyan University) will be visiting Dynamica between the 11th and 14th of March</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/27/old-5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prof. Reinhold Blümel (Wesleyan University) will be visiting Dynamica between the 11th and 14th of March" /><published>2019-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/27/old-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/27/old-5.html">&lt;p&gt;Prof. Reinhold Blümel (Wesleyan Uni., Middeltown, CT), a long time collaborator will be among us from the 11th to the 14th of March and will give
2 talks to the community. The &lt;strong&gt;first one&lt;/strong&gt; is meant for a wider audience and will be given on Tuesday the 12th of March 15h30 as a departmental colloquium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title 1&lt;/strong&gt; : QUANTUM COMPUTERS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt; : &lt;em&gt;Finally! Quantum computers are here!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We can either buy them outright, or access them via the internet! As a consequence, university and industry-based education in quantum computing is growing, essential quantum workforce is scarce, and governments all over the globe have funded quantum initiatives worth billions of dollars for research and development of quantum computers. Quantum computing has emerged from the realm of pure academic research and is now a staple of industrial research and development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quantum computing has reached criticality, is taking off, and it’s an excellent time to hop on board!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After briefly reviewing the history of quantum computing, and explaining why quantum computers are so much faster than “classical” computers, I will provide an overview of current players in the market together with their products.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The extraordinary levels of government funding currently pouring into quantum computing underscore the importance of quantum computing for the near and not-
so-near future.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;second talk&lt;/strong&gt; of a more technical nature and is scheduled for the next day (location and time to be announced). It reads&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title 2&lt;/strong&gt; : HOW TO MAKE A QUANTUM COMPUTER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;While there are any number of ways to realize a qubit, two types of quantum computer architectures have emerged as the leading contenders for realizing a quantum computer:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(1) trapped ions and (2) Josephson junctions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After a brief overview over quantum computing companies and their preferred architectures, I’ll focus exclusively on how to build a quantum computer based on trapped-ion technology. As an example I will discuss the types of quantum computers that have already been built at research labs at the University of Maryland. These computers use trapped Yb ions and realize the computational qubit as one of the hyperfine transitions in Yb^+. Advantages and problems of the ion-trap architecture will be discussed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Prof. Reinhold Blümel (Wesleyan Uni., Middeltown, CT), a long time collaborator will be among us from the 11th to the 14th of March and will give 2 talks to the community. The first one is meant for a wider audience and will be given on Tuesday the 12th of March 15h30 as a departmental colloquium.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Learning for Aquaculture</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/27/old-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Learning for Aquaculture" /><published>2019-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/27/old-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/27/old-3.html">&lt;p&gt;Dr. Vincent Marceau, former member of Dynamica (M.Sc. 2009-11) is to present in the Physics Department his recent involvement into machine learning in an industrial context. The title of his talk is Deep Learning for Aquaculture.
Not to be missed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dr. Vincent Marceau, former member of Dynamica (M.Sc. 2009-11) is to present in the Physics Department his recent involvement into machine learning in an industrial context. The title of his talk is Deep Learning for Aquaculture. Not to be missed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A self-organized workshop on Network Science in Charlevoix</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/26/old-7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A self-organized workshop on Network Science in Charlevoix" /><published>2019-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/26/old-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/26/old-7.html">&lt;p&gt;From the 16th to the 22nd of February, the second edition of the Dynamica workshop retreats (a.k.a Rezoo) took place in Charlevoix. These events are completely organized by the students, with a sole purpose : make collaborative, bold and above all, original science in an idyllic environment.
It is also a unique opportunity for the seniors in the group to share their knowledge and their experience with the new members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This edition was led by Edward Laurence, along with Charles Murphy, Guillaume St-Onge, Xavier Roy-Pomerleau and Vincent Thibeault. The topic of the workshop was to adapt and develop new methods to infer the change point, and the source of the change, for dynamical processes taking place on networks. During this one week retreat, the team exploited and tested two perspectives to perform this task : Bayesian Statistics and Machine Learning. Spoiler alert : it was a success, and without a doubt, it is expected that a publication will emerge from this workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the participants want to express their sincere gratitude towards the Sentinel North program and the Pr. Antoine Allard for their financial support
–without their commitment, such highly formative events could not be realized. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">From the 16th to the 22nd of February, the second edition of the Dynamica workshop retreats (a.k.a Rezoo) took place in Charlevoix. These events are completely organized by the students, with a sole purpose : make collaborative, bold and above all, original science in an idyllic environment. It is also a unique opportunity for the seniors in the group to share their knowledge and their experience with the new members.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ph. D. thesis added to the Board of Honour of the Faculty of Graduate Studies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/08/old-8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ph. D.  thesis added to the Board of Honour of the Faculty of Graduate Studies" /><published>2018-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/08/old-8</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/08/old-8.html">&lt;p&gt;After careful examination, the evaluation committee has given the highest overall mark (excellent) to the Doctoral thesis of Jean-Gabriel Young.
Therefore, the name of the author will be added to the Board of Honour of the Faculty of Graduate Studies. It perpetuates the group’s tradition of excellence, with 9 theses added to the Board of Honour in 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations are not only a good idea, but another occasion (as if we needed an excuse) for celebration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After careful examination, the evaluation committee has given the highest overall mark (excellent) to the Doctoral thesis of Jean-Gabriel Young. Therefore, the name of the author will be added to the Board of Honour of the Faculty of Graduate Studies. It perpetuates the group’s tradition of excellence, with 9 theses added to the Board of Honour in 10 years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stochastic Block Model goes universal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/27/old-4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stochastic Block Model goes universal" /><published>2018-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/27/old-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/27/old-4.html">&lt;p&gt;In the latest published contribution of Dynamica, Mesoscopic Pattern Extraction (MPE) and SBM share central stage. Under the evocative title
“Universality of the SBM”, MPE is considered under the looking glass of the SBM. The Abstract tells some of the story. “MPE is the problem of finding a partition of the nodes of a complex network that maximizes some objective function. Many well-known network inference problems fall in this category,
including, for instance, community detection, core-periphery identification,
and imperfect graph coloring. In this paper, we show that the most popular algorithms designed to solve MPE problems can in fact be understood as special cases of the maximum likelihood formulation of the stochastic block model
(SBM) or one of its direct generalizations. These equivalence relations show that the SBM is nearly universal with respect to MPE problems.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to the full text and preprints are available on the Publication page.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In the latest published contribution of Dynamica, Mesoscopic Pattern Extraction (MPE) and SBM share central stage. Under the evocative title “Universality of the SBM”, MPE is considered under the looking glass of the SBM. The Abstract tells some of the story. “MPE is the problem of finding a partition of the nodes of a complex network that maximizes some objective function. Many well-known network inference problems fall in this category, including, for instance, community detection, core-periphery identification, and imperfect graph coloring. In this paper, we show that the most popular algorithms designed to solve MPE problems can in fact be understood as special cases of the maximum likelihood formulation of the stochastic block model (SBM) or one of its direct generalizations. These equivalence relations show that the SBM is nearly universal with respect to MPE problems.”</summary></entry></feed>